<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Security on Namaste</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in Security on Namaste</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright © 2016–2030, Pranav Kumar</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pranav083.github.io/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Master's Projects Portfolio</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/readme/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/readme/</guid><description>
Welcome to my graduate research and coursework portfolio. This page showcases projects across 3 semesters of my master's degree, spanning computer architecture, systems programming, compiler optimization, operating systems, and distributed systems security.
Semester 1 (Fall 2024) - Computer Architecture &amp;amp; Hardware Cache Optimization on RISC-V Architecture Hardware Architecture
Optimizes CPU cache performance through comparative analysis of LRU (Least Recently Used) and PLRU (Pseudo-LRU) replacement policies. Benchmarks FFT and SHA-256 algorithms on a custom RISC-V core, analyzing performance characteristics and memory access patterns.</description></item><item><title>IoT Security Case Study: Edge AI &amp; Federated Learning in Smart Grids</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-iot-security/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-iot-security/</guid><description>
Course: IoT Security &amp;amp; Privacy | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Threat Modeling, Privacy-Preserving ML, Critical Infrastructure Protection
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation The electrical grid is critical national infrastructure (150M+ customers). Modernization through smart grid technology introduces connectivity benefits but expands attack surface. Energy sector attacks increased 65% YoY (2021-2023). This project investigates: How can federated learning + differential privacy enable real-time grid optimization while provably protecting customer privacy and maintaining security posture?</description></item></channel></rss>