<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pranav Kumar - Graduate Student &amp; Systems Engineer on Namaste</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Pranav Kumar - Graduate Student &amp; Systems Engineer on Namaste</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright © 2016–2030, Pranav Kumar</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pranav083.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Master's Projects Portfolio</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/readme/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/readme/</guid><description>
Welcome to my graduate research and coursework portfolio. This page showcases projects across 3 semesters of my master's degree, spanning computer architecture, systems programming, compiler optimization, operating systems, and distributed systems security.
Semester 1 (Fall 2024) - Computer Architecture &amp;amp; Hardware Cache Optimization on RISC-V Architecture Hardware Architecture
Optimizes CPU cache performance through comparative analysis of LRU (Least Recently Used) and PLRU (Pseudo-LRU) replacement policies. Benchmarks FFT and SHA-256 algorithms on a custom RISC-V core, analyzing performance characteristics and memory access patterns.</description></item><item><title>Concurrent Data Structures: Memory Reclamation Benchmarking (SEIZE)</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-seize-concurrent/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-seize-concurrent/</guid><description>
Concurrent Data Structures: Memory Reclamation Benchmarking (SEIZE) Course: Advanced Systems - Concurrent Programming | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Lock-Free Algorithms, Memory Safety, Performance Analysis
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Lock-free data structures eliminate mutex bottlenecks but create memory reclamation challenges: how to safely free nodes when concurrent threads might still read them? This project investigates a critical trade-off: Which memory reclamation scheme offers the best latency/throughput/memory-usage profile across diverse workloads on modern multi-core systems?</description></item><item><title>File System Consistency Checker (xv6 fsck)</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-xv6-filesystem/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-xv6-filesystem/</guid><description>
Course: CS 5204 - Advanced Operating Systems Project 1 | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Crash Consistency, File System Reliability, Recovery Algorithms
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation File systems can become corrupted when systems crash mid-operation. xv6's simple inode/block-based design is vulnerable to inconsistencies: orphaned inodes, dangling references, multiply-allocated blocks. This project implements an fsck tool addressing: How to detect and repair filesystem corruption following xv6 design principles while minimizing I/O overhead?</description></item><item><title>IoT Security Case Study: Edge AI &amp; Federated Learning in Smart Grids</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-iot-security/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-iot-security/</guid><description>
Course: IoT Security &amp;amp; Privacy | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Threat Modeling, Privacy-Preserving ML, Critical Infrastructure Protection
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation The electrical grid is critical national infrastructure (150M+ customers). Modernization through smart grid technology introduces connectivity benefits but expands attack surface. Energy sector attacks increased 65% YoY (2021-2023). This project investigates: How can federated learning + differential privacy enable real-time grid optimization while provably protecting customer privacy and maintaining security posture?</description></item><item><title>Virtual Memory Analysis: Page Table Walker</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-page-table-walker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-page-table-walker/</guid><description>
Course: CS 5204 - Advanced Operating Systems Project 2 | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Virtual Memory Management, Page Table Structures, TLB Behavior
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Modern systems use multi-level page tables for virtual-to-physical (VA→PA) address translation. Understanding memory layout is critical for optimization and debugging. This project investigates: How do different allocation strategies produce distinct physical memory layouts, and what's the performance impact on TLB efficiency and cache behavior?</description></item><item><title>Advanced Linux Kernel Modules &amp; Performance Monitoring</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-kernel-modules/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-kernel-modules/</guid><description>
Course: Advanced Linux Kernel | Semester: Spring 2025
Technical Focus: Kernel-Space Systems, Memory Allocation Strategies, Device Driver Architecture
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Kernel development traditionally requires unsafe C for performance; safety violations cause system crashes. Rust in Linux kernel (since 6.1) provides memory safety without garbage collection—but integrating Rust with C-based kernel interfaces requires careful API design. This project addresses: Can Rust effectively replace C for kernel subsystems while maintaining performance and safety?</description></item><item><title>LLVM Optimization Passes: Function Analysis &amp; Local Optimizations</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-llvm-optimization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-llvm-optimization/</guid><description>
Course: Compiler Optimization | Semester: Spring 2025
Technical Focus: IR Analysis, Pass Infrastructure, Optimization Algorithms
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation LLVM's optimization infrastructure provides extensibility but lacks accessible tutorials for custom passes. Students must navigate complex APIs: Function, BasicBlock, Instruction, PassManager. This project addresses: Can we build composable, teachable analysis and optimization passes that integrate seamlessly with LLVM's infrastructure while maintaining correctness and reasonable compile-time performance?
Research Context IR Design: LLVM IR balances expressiveness (language-independent) with analyzability Analysis-Driven Optimization: Modern compilers run analysis before optimization; separate concerns improve maintainability Performance Sensitivity: Compiler must complete quickly; passes can't dominate compilation time Teachability: Many students struggle with LLVM's trait system and C++ template complexity System Architecture &amp;amp; Design LLVM Compilation Pipeline 1Source Code (C/C++/Rust/etc) 2 │ 3 ▼ 4Frontend Codegen (Clang/Rustc) 5 │ 6 ▼ 7LLVM IR (Text/Bitcode) 8 │ 9 ├─ PassManager 10 │ ├─ Analysis Passes (FunctionInfo, LoopAnalysis) 11 │ ├─ Transform Passes (LocalOpts, Inlining) 12 │ └─ Verification Passes 13 │ 14 ▼ 15Optimized IR 16 │ 17 ▼ 18Backend (DAGISel, RegAlloc, AsmPrinter) 19 │ 20 ▼ 21Machine Code FunctionInfo Analysis Pass Purpose: Gather information about function structure, loops, recursion without modifying code.</description></item><item><title>Register Allocation Optimization through Coalescing &amp; Live Range Splitting</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-register-allocation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-register-allocation/</guid><description>
Course: Compiler Design - Advanced Topics | Semester: Spring 2025
Technical Focus: Graph Coloring, Register Pressure, Code Generation
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Register allocation is the compiler's final opportunity to improve code quality before machine code generation. Modern CPUs have 16-32 integer registers, but functions often need more virtual registers. The allocator must: minimize spill code (memory loads/stores), reduce register pressure, and complete quickly. This project investigates: Can aggressive coalescing combined with smart live range splitting outperform LLVM's standard greedy allocator on real benchmarks?</description></item><item><title>Cache Optimization on RISC-V Architecture</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s1-ece5504-cache-optimization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s1-ece5504-cache-optimization/</guid><description>
Course: ECE 5504 - Computer Architecture | Semester: Fall 2024
Technical Focus: Memory Hierarchy Design, Replacement Algorithms, Performance Modeling
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Cache design involves fundamental trade-offs between performance and hardware complexity. Least Recently Used (LRU) replacement achieves optimal miss rates asymptotically but requires O(n) comparisons per access and O(n) state maintenance in n-way associative caches. Pseudo-LRU (PLRU) reduces complexity to O(log n) with tree-based bit vectors—but at what performance cost?</description></item><item><title>Control Android on Ubuntu with Internet</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/content/post/project/linux_android/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 23:32:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/content/post/project/linux_android/</guid><description>
How to Control Your Android Device with Ubuntu Using Scrcpy Are you someone who uses their Android device to access the internet but doesn't have Wi-Fi access? Do you wish to control your Android device from your Ubuntu computer?
If yes, then Scrcpy is the perfect solution for you. In this blog post, we'll guide you through the process of casting and controlling your Android device on Ubuntu using Scrcpy. And luckily, this is a great software called Scrcpy that makes this process a breeze.</description></item></channel></rss>