<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Optimization Passes on Namaste</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/tags/optimization-passes/</link><description>Recent content in Optimization Passes on Namaste</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright © 2016–2030, Pranav Kumar</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pranav083.github.io/tags/optimization-passes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>LLVM Optimization Passes: Function Analysis &amp; Local Optimizations</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-llvm-optimization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-llvm-optimization/</guid><description>
Course: Compiler Optimization | Semester: Spring 2025
Technical Focus: IR Analysis, Pass Infrastructure, Optimization Algorithms
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation LLVM's optimization infrastructure provides extensibility but lacks accessible tutorials for custom passes. Students must navigate complex APIs: Function, BasicBlock, Instruction, PassManager. This project addresses: Can we build composable, teachable analysis and optimization passes that integrate seamlessly with LLVM's infrastructure while maintaining correctness and reasonable compile-time performance?
Research Context IR Design: LLVM IR balances expressiveness (language-independent) with analyzability Analysis-Driven Optimization: Modern compilers run analysis before optimization; separate concerns improve maintainability Performance Sensitivity: Compiler must complete quickly; passes can't dominate compilation time Teachability: Many students struggle with LLVM's trait system and C++ template complexity System Architecture &amp;amp; Design LLVM Compilation Pipeline 1Source Code (C/C++/Rust/etc) 2 │ 3 ▼ 4Frontend Codegen (Clang/Rustc) 5 │ 6 ▼ 7LLVM IR (Text/Bitcode) 8 │ 9 ├─ PassManager 10 │ ├─ Analysis Passes (FunctionInfo, LoopAnalysis) 11 │ ├─ Transform Passes (LocalOpts, Inlining) 12 │ └─ Verification Passes 13 │ 14 ▼ 15Optimized IR 16 │ 17 ▼ 18Backend (DAGISel, RegAlloc, AsmPrinter) 19 │ 20 ▼ 21Machine Code FunctionInfo Analysis Pass Purpose: Gather information about function structure, loops, recursion without modifying code.</description></item></channel></rss>