<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rust on Namaste</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/tags/rust/</link><description>Recent content in Rust on Namaste</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright © 2016–2030, Pranav Kumar</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pranav083.github.io/tags/rust/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Concurrent Data Structures: Memory Reclamation Benchmarking (SEIZE)</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-seize-concurrent/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s3-seize-concurrent/</guid><description>
Concurrent Data Structures: Memory Reclamation Benchmarking (SEIZE) Course: Advanced Systems - Concurrent Programming | Semester: Fall 2025
Technical Focus: Lock-Free Algorithms, Memory Safety, Performance Analysis
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Lock-free data structures eliminate mutex bottlenecks but create memory reclamation challenges: how to safely free nodes when concurrent threads might still read them? This project investigates a critical trade-off: Which memory reclamation scheme offers the best latency/throughput/memory-usage profile across diverse workloads on modern multi-core systems?</description></item><item><title>Advanced Linux Kernel Modules &amp; Performance Monitoring</title><link>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-kernel-modules/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranav083.github.io/post/project/s2-kernel-modules/</guid><description>
Course: Advanced Linux Kernel | Semester: Spring 2025
Technical Focus: Kernel-Space Systems, Memory Allocation Strategies, Device Driver Architecture
Problem Statement &amp;amp; Motivation Kernel development traditionally requires unsafe C for performance; safety violations cause system crashes. Rust in Linux kernel (since 6.1) provides memory safety without garbage collection—but integrating Rust with C-based kernel interfaces requires careful API design. This project addresses: Can Rust effectively replace C for kernel subsystems while maintaining performance and safety?</description></item></channel></rss>